<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mayers catechisme abridged. Or the A.B.C. inlarged With many necessary questions fitted vnto it, for the benefit of all that desire to teach or learne it effectually. A duty to which all wee of the Church of England are bound, it being generally appointed by authoritie.</title>
            <author>Mayer, John, 1583-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07354</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17739</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842752</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842752</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07354)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 681:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mayers catechisme abridged. Or the A.B.C. inlarged With many necessary questions fitted vnto it, for the benefit of all that desire to teach or learne it effectually. A duty to which all wee of the Church of England are bound, it being generally appointed by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Mayer, John, 1583-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition made more compleat and perfect by the author.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M[athewes] for I. M[arriot] and are to be sold by Iohn Grismand, at his shop in Pauls Alley, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Mayer.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E (-E8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:1"/>
            <p>MAYERS CATECHISME ABRIDGED.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> The <hi>A.B.C.</hi> inlarged.</p>
            <p>With many neceſſary Queſtions fitted vnto it, for the benefit of all that deſire to teach or learne <hi>it effectually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A dutie to which all wee of the</hi> Church of England are bound, it being generally appointed <hi>by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition made more compleat <hi>and perfect by the Author.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>I. M.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Griſmand,</hi> at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Alley, at the Signe of the Gun. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:2"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, loe here I offer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee the ſecond time, the Briefe of my larger Tract. Thou haſt beene once abuſed by the temeritie and indiſcretion of the Stationer, offering thee the <hi>Engliſh Teacher;</hi> a title none of mine, and an imperfect confuſed Chaos of Queſtions and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, whereof I was much aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. To amend this fault, and to ſatisfie the longing deſire of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I haue done that which here thou ſeeſt. And I doe now aſſure
<pb facs="tcp:7436:3"/>thee of a perfect Catechiſme, containing the ſubſtance both of Text and Comment compleat, wherein is both milke for Babes, and ſtronger meate for ſuch as haue attained more growth in knowledge. The milke is in a greater Character, which if you pleaſe, may be firſt learned tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: the ſtronger meate is in a character ſomwhat leſſer. Read, conſider, and vſe all according to thy diſcretion, but be ſure to vſe it, or ſome like vnto it for the common good of Vniformitie and Order; and the God of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der graunt, that wee may ſo lay the foundation of the light of truth here, as that wee may attaine the light of glorie heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:3"/>
            <head>A Prayer to bee vſed <hi>before the reading of</hi> Bookes of Pietie, or Inſtruction.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
               </hi> God that art the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Lights, enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten my darkned vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that I may ſee into the wonders contained in the Law. Diſpell in me the miſtie clouds of ignorance, expell the loue of darkneſſe, and repell the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Law of ſinne. Sanctifie my wit, that I may bee able to retaine, and rectifie my will, that I may obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſubmit my ſelfe to thy good will in all things. Thou which art the Maſter-builder of thine owne
<pb facs="tcp:7436:4"/>houſe, ſettle me as one of thy liuing ſtones vpon the right foundation, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> in whom I may daily grow vp, till that all the building, coupled together, groweth to an holy Temple in the Lord. And this I craue in the name of thy deare Son, my moſt bleſſed Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>MAYERS CATECHISME ABRIDGED, <hi>OR</hi> The A. B. C. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is your name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>F. or E.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why doth the Catechiſme begin with this queſtion touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the name doth ſerue to put vs in minde of our Chriſtian profeſsion, to which we betake our ſelues in Baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who gaue you this name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:5"/>A. <hi>My godfathers, and my god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers in my Baptiſme, wherein I was made a member of Chriſt a child of God, and an inheritor of the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is Baptiſme of that vertue, that by the outward waſhing thereof, eueryone is made a member of Chriſt, the child of God and inheritor of the Kingdome of Heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.5.</note> No, for vnleſſe a man bee borne againe of water, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why then ſayſt thou, that by Baptiſme thou art made a member of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe baptiſme is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of regeneration, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may rightly ſay, that wee are thereby Sacramentally made the members of Chriſt, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and in the iudgement of Charity hold the ſame touching all others, that are baptized</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What did your godfathers and godmothers then for you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>They did promiſe and vow,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:5"/>thrée things in my name. Firſt, that I ſhould forſake the Deuill, and all his workes, and pomps, the vanities of this wicked world, and all the ſinfull luſts of the fleſh. Secondly, that I ſhould beléeue all the articles of the Chriſtian faith: And thirdly, that I ſhould kéepe gods holy Will and Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and walke in the ſame all the dayes of my life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>VVhat need is there, that any ſhould ſtand thus to promiſe for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in their Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is great need for the more aſſurance of the Church, into which the childe is by baptiſme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is the Church the more aſſured thus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe hee is not onely bound in duty now, but alſo by vow ſolemnly made before all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doſt thou thinke then, that thou art bound to doe, as thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and godmothers promiſed for thée?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:6"/>A. <hi>Yes verily: and by Gods helpe ſo I will. And I heartily thanke our heauenly Father, that he hath called me to this ſtate of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through Ieſus Chriſt our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. And I pray God to giue me his grace, that I may continue in the ſame vnto my liues end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Thou ſaydſt that thou were bound by vow in baptiſme to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue all the Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith, let me therefore heare thée rehearſe theſe Articles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I beléeue in God the Father Almighty, Maker of heauen and earth. And in Ieſus Chriſt his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne our Lord, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin Mary, ſuffered vnder Ponce Pilate: was crucified, dead, and buried: he deſcended into hell: The third day he roſe againe from the dead: He aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father Almighty: From thence hée ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beléeue in the holy Ghoſt: The holy Catholike
<pb facs="tcp:7436:6"/>Church: The communion of Saints: the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: The reſurrection of the body: And the life euerlaſting, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doſt thou chiefly learne in theſe Articles of thy beliefe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, I learne to beléeue in God the Father, who hath made me and all the world. Secondly, in God the Sonne who hath redéemed mée and all mankind. Thirdly, in God the holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth mée, and all the elect people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How knoweſt thou that there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Many waies:
<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15. 1. Cor. 2.11.</note> but chiefly by mine owne conſcience, accuſing me for ſecret ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth this proue that there is a God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It proueth an infinite wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that knowes the moſt ſecret thoughts of the heart, ſuch as is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, deuill, nor Angell, but God alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many Gods be there?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 8.6. Deut. 4.39.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>But one onely true God, the reſt are Idols ſet vp by man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:7"/>Q. <hi>What is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>God is a Spirit,
<note place="margin">Exod. 3.14. Ioh. 2.24. Ier. 2.24. Pſal. 139.8.</note> infinite, moſt holy, onely wiſe, moſt merciful, iuſt, and Almighty, of whoſe dayes there is no beginning nor end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Into how many Perſons is the God-head deſtinguiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Into thrée, the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If in the God-head there bée thrée perſons, and euery one be God, how ſay you then that there is but one God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.7.</note> 
               <hi>There is but one onely Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, one Infinite power and one Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which words learne you to beléeue in God the Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In theſe words; I beléeue in God, the Father Almighty, Maker of heauen and earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Declare more fully the faith comprehended in this Article.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.18. 1. Ioh. 3.9. Gen. 17.1. Reu. 1.8. Pſal. 104. Iob 39. c. 40</note> 
               <hi>I learne to beléeue, that God is my Father, able to doe al things; the Creator of the whole world, and the Lord and Gouernour of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:7"/>Q. <hi>Thou ſaidſt that thou didſt learne to beléeue in God the Sonne, which redéemed thée &amp; all mankind, what did God the Sonne for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of mankind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two things: firſt, hee was humbled: ſecondly, he was exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>wherein ſtandeth his humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In thrée degrées.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt degrée?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, he was made man,
<note place="margin">Math. 1. Luke 1.2. Eſa. 7.14.</note> for he was conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgin</hi> Mary.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How can this be, that God ſhould be made man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Not by turning the Godhead into the nature of man, but by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king mans nature vnto the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, that ſo one perſon might bee both God and Man.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond degree?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>He ſuffered the death of the Croſſe for my ſinnes: for he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder</hi> Pontius Pilate, <hi>was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, dead, and buried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What neede was there, that the Sonne of God ſhould thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe
<pb facs="tcp:7436:8"/>himſelfe for vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Great need on our part, who could not be deliuered by Angels,
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 1.7. 1 Pet. 1.8.</note> or by earthly Treaſures, but onely by his blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth ſinne deſerue ſo ill, that we could not by other meanes be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered here from, but by the death of the Sonne of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Yes, it deſerues the infinite curſe of the Law,
<note place="margin">Deu. 27.28 Rom. 6.23.</note> that is, all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this world, and euerlaſting damnation in the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If hee muſt néeds be made fit to beare the curſe, why did hee not take ſome other nature more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent vnto him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Man onely had ſinned, and it was moſt agréeable to the Iuſtice of God to receiue the payment of the debt of ſin in the ſame nature which committed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came it to be thus with vs men? were we made ſinners?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.27. Eccleſ. 7.31. Geneſ. 3. Rom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>No, God at the firſt made man righteous, but by yéelding to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils temptation, hee made himſelfe a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:8"/>Q. <hi>Wherein did man yéeld to the temptation of the deuill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In eating of the forbidden fruit, and not contenting himſelfe with all other fruits, of which the Lord had allowed him to eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Was God ſo angry that hée would curſe man for eating an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or figge, or ſuch like?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That was not the matter of Gods anger, but his vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, pride, diſobedience, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting rather the deuill, then God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But though one man did thus, yet all did not, are we all then ſinners, and vnder the curſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>We were all in his loynes, and ſo whatſoeuer he did, and what eſtate he fell into, it is Common to vs all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>It ſéemes then, that we are ſinners ſo ſoone as we are borne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we haue actually done ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or euill?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Yes verily, the child that is but new borne, yea, but conceiued,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5. Rom. 5.12.</note> and liuing in his Mothers wombe, is a ſinner, and néedeth Gods grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:9"/>Q. <hi>But as we are all ſinners, are we all againe deliuered without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe thou ſayſt, that hee hath redeemed all mankinde?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He hath payde a price ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to redeeme all, neither doth hee exclude any from the benefit thereof, but onely ſuch as exclude themſelues.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All vnbeleeuers, or ſuch, as though they beare themſelues vpon their faith, liue according to the fleſh, and not according the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third degrée of his humiliation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.9. 1. Pet. 3.19. Pſal. 16 30.</note> 
               <hi>He deſcended into hell that I might be deliuered from hell, and euerlaſting death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Js this all the humiliation of the Sonne of God for our redemption, did hee no way elſe abaſe himſelfe for vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, he became obedient to the Law alſo,
<note place="margin">Gal. 4.4. 1. Cor. 1 30. Rom. 8.3.</note> that by his obedience and righteouſneſſe wee might ſtand perfectly righteous in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:9"/>Q. <hi>Wherein ſtandeth his exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>In foure degrées.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſtion <hi>Which is the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, the third day he roſe againe from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Secondly, he aſcended vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Thirdly, hée ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That hée hath all honour, power, and authority in heauen and in earth together with God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>Which is the fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Fourthly, from thence he ſhall come to Iudge the quicke and the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Thou ſaydſt, that thou didſt chiefly learne in the Articles of thy faith, to beléeue in God the Father, ſo that it ſeemeth there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb facs="tcp:7436:10"/>more, yet to hée learned by theſe Articles, what is that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I beléeue the holy Catholike Church, the communion of Saints, the forgiueneſſe of ſinner, the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the body, and the life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is this Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The whole company of the faithfull, called out from the reſt of the world by the preaching of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is this Church called Holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.7. 1. Pet. 3.9. Eph. 2.19. 1. Ioh. 3.3. Phil. 3.14, 15</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe it is ſanctified, and waſhed by water and the holy Ghoſt; ſtriueth againſt all ſinne, and to be holy, as God is holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why is it called Catholike?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Pro. 7. Acts 2.5. 1. Tim. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe it conſiſteth of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all ſorts, ſcattered all ouer the world and of al times and ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How may a man certainely know, where this Church of God is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.41.47. Eſay 8.20.</note> By theſe two ſpeciall marks, holineſſe taught and profeſſed, and antiquity, when they goe together.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:10"/>Q. <hi>Is not the Church of Rome then the true Church of God, ſeeing it exceeds in holineſſe, and is moſt anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No: it was a true Church indeed in the Apoſtles times, and many yeares after; but now it is neither holy, for great vncleanneſſe is there maintained; nor ancient, for the ancient Religion is defaced with groſſe errours, and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where then may we finde the true Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In England, and in all other places where theſe corruptions are done away, and Religion is reſtored to the firſt purity.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How can this be, ſeeing the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion here profeſſed is but as it were of yeſterday, and neuer heard of before</hi> Luther <hi>and</hi> Caluin?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> This is a meere ſlander; for there was neuer any age ſince the Apoſtles, wherein there haue not beene ſome ſtanding to the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance hereof, againſt Romiſh cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:11"/>Q. <hi>How happened it then, that the Church of Rome ſtill preuailed, and was generally accounted for Chriſts true Church, and thoſe oppugners were neuer of any eſteeme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By the greatneſſe and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Roman Biſhops, whoſe chiefe care it hath been almoſt, euer ſince <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time, to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their owne Church, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to ſuppreſſe their aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But is it poſsible, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church being once a true Church ſhould fall, ſeeing God hath promiſed his Spirit to his Church to be alwaies preſent, leading it into all truth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lord tyeth not his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to any place, for then the famous Churches in Aſia ſhould ſtill haue beene true Churches; but the Spirit is alwaies preſent to the faithfull in all places of the world.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hauing found out the true Church, are wee to beleeue in it, as in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, for then we ſhould ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time beleeue errours, ſeeing the
<pb facs="tcp:7436:11"/>beſt men, which are the Church, may erre.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it then to beleeue the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To beleeue the doctrine of the Church, wherin it followeth Chriſt, the Prophets, and Apoſtles, the only ſure pillars and ground of truth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in theſe Articles,</hi> viz. <hi>The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>They be certaine ſpeciall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſits belonging to the Church, and to euery member thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Communion of Saints?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. Iohn 15. Gal. 3.28. Reuel. 6.11. Heb. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>That holy and ſwéet follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which all the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Chriſts Church haue one with another, in forrowing, reioycing, praying, and praiſing God, for, and with one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That wonderful grace of God in Ieſus Chriſt, whereby hee paſſeth ouer our tranſgreſſions, as if they
<pb facs="tcp:7436:12"/>had neuer béen committed, and relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the puniſhment due to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is the Reſurrection of the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The raiſing of the body againe at the laſt day by Gods power,
<note place="margin">Math. 22.31. Dan. 12.2. Iob 19.25. 1 Cor. 15.</note> that being ioyned to the ſoule, it may ſtand before Gods iudgement Seat, to giue account of all that it hath done, whether good or euill, and bee rewarded accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What manner of bodies ſhall we haue in the Reſurrection?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The very ſame which now we haue, only whereas they be now na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. &amp; 35 43. Iob 19.25.</note> they ſhall riſe againe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, not ſubiect to death any more, nor ſuſtained by naturall meanes, of meates and drinkes, and ſleepe, and the like.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Among thoſe that die, ſome are crooked through age, ſome tender in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, ſome blind, and ſome lame, ſhall their bodies at the reſurrection then bee the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, for all theſe are weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, which ſhall be done away to the faithfull; and ſtrength, perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:12"/>and comelineſſe ſhall be to euery one of them</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the Life euerlaſting?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.11 Eſay 6.1. Reuel. 21. Eſay 66.23. 1 Cor. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>All that euer enduring happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; all thoſe ioyes which the Lord imparteth to al his elect in the world to come, which are ſo great, as that the eye hath not ſéene, nor the eare heard, neither can the heart conceiue throughly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Thou ſaydſt that thou wert bound by vow in thy Baptiſme to kéepe Gods holy will and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements: tell me therefore how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Commandements are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Ten. God ſpake theſe words, and ſaid, I am the Lord thy God, which haue brought thée out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and of Egypt, out of the houſe of bondage. Thou ſhalt haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods but me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnder the earth: Thou ſhalt not vow downe to them, nor worſhip them: for I the Lord thy God am a
<pb facs="tcp:7436:13"/>iealous God, and viſite the ſinnes of the Fathers vpon the Children vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mercy vnto thouſands in them that loue me and kéepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine: for the Lord will not hold him guiltles that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remember that thou kéepe holy the Sabbath day: Sixe dayes thou ſhalt labour, and doe all that thou haſt to doe: but the ſeauenth day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God. In it thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke, thou, and thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy manſeruant, and thy maidſernant, thy cattell, &amp; the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that is within thy gates. For in ſix dayes the Lord made heauen and earth the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeauenth day: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord bleſſed the ſeauenth, day, and hallowed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother, that thy dayes may bee long in the land, which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:13"/>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adultery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ours houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eighbors wife, nor his ſeruant, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s mayd, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, or any thing that is his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doeſt thou learne out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theſe commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two things, my dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ards God, and my dutie towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is thy dutie towards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>My dutie towards God is, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>léeue in him, to feare him, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue him with all my heart, with all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y mind, with all my ſoule, and with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my ſtrength: to worſhip him: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue him thanks: to put my whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſt in him: to call vpon him: to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nour his holy name, and his word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d to ſerue him truely all the dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is thy dutie towards
<pb facs="tcp:7436:14"/>thy neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>My dutie towards my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is, to loue him as my ſelfe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to doe to all men, as I would the ſhould do to me: to loue, honour, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuccour my father and mother: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> honour and obey the King and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſters: to ſubmit my ſelfe to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my Gouernours, Teachers, ſpirit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all Paſtors, and Maſters: to orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my ſelfe lowly, and reuerently to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> my betters: To hurt no body b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> word nor déed: to be true and iuſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all my dealings: to beare no malic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nor hatred in my heart: to kéepe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands from picking and ſtealing, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my tongue from euill ſpeaking, l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, and flaundering: to kéepe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> body in temperance, ſoberneſſe, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chaſtitie: not to couet nor deſire <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther mens goods, but learne and l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour truly to get mine owne liuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and to doe my dutie in that ſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> life, vnto the which is ſhall plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> God to call me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How were theſe Commau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements giuen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Written with Gods own
<pb facs="tcp:7436:14"/>hand in two Tables of ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which Table do you learne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our dutie towards God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In the firſt, containing the foure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rmer Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many bee the parts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ery of theſe Commandements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two, the Commandement it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, and the reaſon of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the firſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which words is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andement contained?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Commaundement is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou ſhalt haue none other Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are wee heere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To haue the Lord for our God, that is, to loue him aboue all,
<note place="margin">Deut. 6.45. Mal. 1.6. Math. 10.26 Pſal. 20.8. Pſal. 125.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feare him aboue all, to put our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hole truſt in him, and to make our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayees to him alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Foure contrary moſt groſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:15"/>A.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1 Iob 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>Atheiſme, which is the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of no God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12 Luk. 12.48</note> 
               <hi>Ignorance, which is a neglec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the knowledge of God, and of his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20. Iohn 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>Prophaneneſſe, which is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſneſſe of God, and of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Eſay 3.9. Col 3.5. Phil. 3 18.</note> 
               <hi>Inward Idolatry, which is the giuing of Gods worſhip vnto creatures, by praying vnto them truſting in them, or by ſetting th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart vpon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the reaſon of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I am the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Egypt, out of the houſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth this reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerne vs, who were neuer in E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gypt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Our Egypt is the ſtate o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corruption, and our bondage i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thraldom to Satan, from which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7436:15"/>Lord our God onely hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, or the likeneſſe of any thing, that is in heauen aboue, or in the earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, or in the water vnder the earth: Thou ſhalt not how downe to them, nor worſhip them. For I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God, and viſite the ſinnes of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vpon the Children, vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew merey vnto theuſands in them that loue me and kéepe my Commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which words is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Commandement is; Thouſhalt not make to thy ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grauen Image, nor the likeneſſe of any thing, that is in heauen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vnder the earth: Thou ſhalt not how downe to them, nor worſhip them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:16"/>Q. <hi>What is heere forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All outward Idolatry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is outward Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Outward Idolatry is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thrée wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Acts 17.29. Deut. 4.15. Eſ. 40.25.</note> by making the Image of God, or of any creature, to bée worſhipped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Secondly,
<note place="margin">Exod. 32. Iudg. 8.27.</note> by falling downe before any Image.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Thirdly,
<note place="margin">2. Kin. 18.4. Iohn 4.20.</note> by ſeruing God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our owne phantaſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1. Co. 11.20. Eſay 1.12. Pſal. 50.16. Mat. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>To performe all outward duries of Gods ſeruice according to his will, reuealed in his Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the reaſon of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>For I the Lord thy God, am a iealous God, and viſite the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third and fourth generation of them that hate me, and ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:7436:16"/>vnto thonſands in them that loue me and kéepe my Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Shall children be puniſhed for their Parents ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, if they follow them in ſinning, they ſhall beare both the puniſhment of their owne, and of their Parents ſinnes alſo.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine: for the Lord will not hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which words is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Commandement is, Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All abuſing of the name of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3. 2. King. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many wayes is the name of God abuſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Six manner of wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By blaſpheming,
<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24. Mat. 5.33.34</note> or giuing
<pb facs="tcp:7436:17"/>occaſion to others to blaſpheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By ſwearing falſly, deceit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully, raſhly, commonly, or by crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By curſing and banning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By vowing things vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or vnlawfull, or by neglecting o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our lawfull vowes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is fifth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By lightly vſing the holy name of God, or his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſixth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By vaine proteſtations and aſſeuerations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we here co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.39 Ephel. 4.29. Phil. 2.10. 2. Cor. 8.19. Mat. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>To glorifie the name of God in all that wée doe, thinke, ſpeake and deſire, and to labour, that others may be wonne by our meanes to do the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the reaſon of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Lord will not hold him guitleſſe that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:17"/>Q. <hi>If there bee ſuch daunger in ſwearing, may a man lawfully ſweare in any caſe whatſoeuer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Without doubt a man may ſometimes and in ſome caſes law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſweare.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>When, and in what caſe may a man ſweare lawfully?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In three caſes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, for the confirming of a ruth, which cannot otherwiſe bee knowne, and yet neceſſary.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> For the ſtrengthening of oneſt leagues made betwixt men.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the laſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Laſtly, being called to weare before a lawfull Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What elſe is required, that our wearing may be lawfull?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Theſe foure things.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Firſt, we muſt ſweare onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſuch a truth as we know to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Secondly, according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owne intent of him, vnto whom,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:18"/>or before whom we ſweare.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Thirdly, we muſt ſweare on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things poſsible and lawfull.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Fourthly, this being a part of Gods worſhip,
<note place="margin">Ier. 4.2, 3.</note> wee muſt doe it with great reuerence.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What if a man ſhall ſweare to an vnlawfull thing, is hee not bound not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to performe his eath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In no wiſe; for ſo he ſhould adde vnto his ſinne of ſwearing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully,
<note place="margin">Acts 23.</note> a further ſinne of doing vnlawfully.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Remember that thou kéep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> holy the Sabbath day: Sixe daye ſhalt thou labour, and doe all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſt to doe: But the ſeuent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> day is the Sabbath of the Lord th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God. In it thou ſhalt doe no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of worke, thou, and thy Sonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and thy daughter, thy Manſeruan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and thy Maidſeruant, thy Cattel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Stranger that is within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> gates. For in ſixe daies the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7436:18"/>made heauen and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeauenth day. Wherefore the Lord bleſſed the ſeauenth day, and hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which words is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Commandement is. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou keepe holy the Sabbath day, ſixe dayes ſhalt thou labour and doe all that thou haſt to doe, but the ſeauenth is the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath of the Lord thy God, in it thou ſhalt doe no manner of worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>What is the duty here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To kéepe holy the Sabbath day, and to be mindfull of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may this be done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By aſſembling together to pray vnto God, and to praiſe him, to heare his holy Word, and receiue the bleſſed Sacraments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this all that is required to the right keeping of the Sabbath day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but wee muſt prepare our ſelues by prayer, and emptying our hearts of ſinne, and meditate
<pb facs="tcp:7436:19"/>vpon Gods Word, ſuffering it to worke in vs, ſo as that we may bee furthred in all holineſſe of life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is there no duty to be done to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our neighbour for the hallowing of this day?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, it is a ſpeciall time of exerciſing mercy by helping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſudden dangers,
<note place="margin">Mark. 3.4. Mat. 12.12. 1. Cor. 16.2.</note> by collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſtributing to the poore, by viſiting the ſick, and reconciling diſſentions amongſt neighbours.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is there any ſet day vnder the new Teſtament thus to be kept holy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, the day which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Sunday, but in the Scripture the Lords day,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.20. Acts 20 7. 1. Cor. 16.1. Reuel. 1.10.</note> or the firſt day in the weeke, is thus to be kept without alteration to the end of the world.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>When doth the Lords day begin and end?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It beginneth in the morning at the dawning of the day, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth next morning likewiſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are we bound to doe the holy duties of Gods worſhip all this time without ceaſing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:19"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, for wee may refreſh our ſelues with eating and drinking,
<note place="margin">Neh. 8, 9, 10 Hoſh. 2.11.</note> ſinging, and muſick, and with any honeſt delight whatſoeuer, whereby the minde is cheared vp, and ioy and gladneſſe befitting the Lords holy day expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What auaileth it then, whether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sabbath beginne in the morning or euening?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, it auaileth much to know the beginning of the Sabbath rightly that wee be not entangled with any wordly buſineſſe vpon it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this all that wee are bound vnto, to keepe the Sabbath our ſelues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ceaſing from labour, and doing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uties thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but who ſo hath ſonne or laughter, man-ſeruant, or maid,
<note place="margin">Exo. 12.21. Ioſh. 24.15. 1. Tim. 3.15. Epheſ. 6.5.</note> cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell or ſtranger within his gates, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>like bound to prouide as much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n him lieth, that they all obſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his day in their kinde, both man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd beaſt.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth the Lord only take care for he right ſpending of this day, &amp; leaue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to our ſelues vpon the ſixe dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:20"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> No doubtleſſe, but it is his will and commandement alſo,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.28. 2. Theſ. 3.10.12.</note> that we ſhould vpon the ſixe dayes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from idleneſſe, and diligently labour in the works of our callings.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Is it not lawfull then to forbeare working, to attend vpon God and his worſhip, vpon the ſixe dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17 2 Tim. 1. Deut. 6 7. Dan. 6.</note> Yes. It is not onely lawfull, but neceſſary for euery one to doe the duties of Gods worſhip euery day of the weeke, in priuate and in publike, when iuſt occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How can this ſtand with the command of working vpon the ſixe dayes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, very well; becauſe that howſoeuer God is to be ſerued vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſixe dayes, yet they are for the moſt part to bee ſpent in the workes of our callings.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>What more ſpeciall rules are we to follow in our weekely deuotion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Theſe fiue?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Wee muſt pray euery day, morning and euening.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:20"/>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Before and after the vſe of Gods creatures.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The more our neceſsities vrge vs, pray the oftner, and more inſtantly.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Let no day paſſe without ſome reading, and Diuine medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fift?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5.13. Heb. 3.13. 1. Tim. 4.13 Amos 12.</note> Neglect not the publike preaching in the weeke-dayes, where opportunity is offered to come vnto it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is to be thought of whole dayes ſet apart to publike duties in the weeke, as Saints dayes, and dayes of thankeſgiuing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſter 9.21. Mal. 4.59. Iohn 10.22.23. Leuit. 23.</note> All this may lawfully bee done, and is commendable by Gods word, and therefore wee are reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently to conforme our ſelues to the ordinance of authority herein.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the ſinne by this Commandement forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw, <hi>All prophaning of the
<pb facs="tcp:7436:21"/>Sabbath day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is the Sabbath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thrée manner of wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By doing worldly workes, which are not of preſent neceſſity, by iournying about worldly, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, idle reſting, or abſenting our ſelues from the publique duties o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>By forgetfulneſſe of the Sabbath vpon the ſixe dayes, by which wee often bring vpon our ſelues a neceſſitie of prophauing the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>When being Parents or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours, wée leaue our Children, Pupils, or Sernants to their owne liberties vpon this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the reaſons of this Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>They are partly infolded in the Commandement, and partly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in theſe words: For in ſix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dayes the Lord made heauen and
<pb facs="tcp:7436:21"/>earth, the, ſea, and all that therein is, and reſted the ſenenth day, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord bleſſed the ſeuenth day and hollowed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What, and how many are the reaſons infolded in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thrée.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe the Law of the Sabbath is ancient, and was in force in Paradiſe, before mans fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe it is moſt equall, the Lord allowing vs ſixe dayes for our worldly affaires, and requiring but one of ſeuen for the worke of his worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe the ſeuenth is the Lords peculiar day, ſo that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſacriledge we cannot any way prophane it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the reaſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>From the Lords owne exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:22"/>who reſted vpon the ſeuenth day from all his works of creation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>From his bleſſing inſeperably linked to the hallowing of this day, ſo that he which kéepeth it holy, ſhall finde it to his comfort vnto him a bleſſed day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In which Table do you learne your dutie toward your neighbour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In the ſecond Table, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſix latter commandements.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Reherſe the firſt of theſe, which is the fift Commandement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Honour thy father &amp; mother, that thy dayes may bee long in the land, which the Lord thy God giueth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To honour father &amp; mother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who are meant by father and mother?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">2 Kings 5.13 Gen. 45.8. 1 Cor. 4.15 2 King 6.21 Iob 31.18. 1 Tim. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Our naturall Parents, the Magiſtrates, who are the parents of our Country; the Miniſters of Gods Word, who are our Fathers in Chriſt; our Maſters and Gouernors,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:22"/>the Ancient, and all our betters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is meant by this word, Honour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To honour, is to loue, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, cheriſh and obey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are all Superiours then to be obeyed and reuerenced?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.1. Col. 2.20. Rom. 13.1. 1 Per. 2.13. 1 Tim. 5.17 1 Theſ. 5.12</note> 
               <hi>They are all to be reuerenced and obeied in the Lord, whoſe image in a ſpeciall manner they beare, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Magiſtrates, Miniſters, and Gouernors for their authoritie, the Ancient, and other Superiours for their wiſedome, experience, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is it our dutie alſo to cheriſh and maintaine them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>It is our dutie to giue main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to the Magiſtrate and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.6 1 Cor. 9. Gal. 6.5. Math. 15.3</note> who ſpend their whole time in doing publike Seruice, and to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, &amp; aged perſons being in want.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is there no dutie required of Superiours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Ephe. 6.4. Col. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>It is the dutie of Superiours to walke worthy the honour due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, and to vſe all gentleneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Inferiours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:23"/>Q. <hi>What is here then forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Exod. 21.17. Deut. 17.10. Ephe. 6.9. Col. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>All irrenerence, diſobedience, and neglect toward thoſe that his in place and authoritie aboue vs, and churliſh behauiour in ſuch toward thoſe that be of a low degrée.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Whence is the reaſon of this Commandement taken?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>From the promiſe of long life, if God pleaſe not to preuent vs with the bleſſing of eternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the firth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Sam. 31.4. Math. 27.5</note> 
               <hi>All vnlawfull killing of our ſelues, or of other men, and all the degrées hereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are theſe degrées?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The degrées of vnlawfull kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are ſixe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Kin. 21 19 Acts 8.1. Deut. 21.7.</note> 
               <hi>The approbation of murther either by command, counſell, conſent, or concealement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Exod. 21.24. Eſay 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>All injurious actions, tending to the preiudice of our neighbors life</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:23"/>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Math. 5.22. Iam. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>All rayling and reuiling ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22</note> 
               <hi>All murdrous deſires and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the heart, as of anger, malice, hatred, and enuy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fifth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.15</note> 
               <hi>All cruelty towards the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſheweth a murtherous mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All impatience, and diſcontent with our eſtate,
<note place="margin">Deut. 22.7.</note> the very high way to moſt horrible murthers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Out of the loue which wee beare to our neighbour,
<note place="margin">Iob 31.19. 1 Kin. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13 Hebr. 10.25 Gal. 6.1.</note> as much as in vs lyeth, to preſerue his life and health, and ſpecially the life of his ſoule, by good counſell, exhortation, and admonition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the ſeuenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:24"/>A. <hi>All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſhly uncleanneſſe both in outward act, and inward concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde, and all occaſions thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the uncleanneſſes in outward act?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Gal. 5.17. 1 C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.6. Rom. 1. Ephe. 5.12</note> 
               <hi>Adultery, Fornication, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, Sodometry, &amp;c. which are ſo ſouſe, that it is a ſhame to name them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is vncleanneſſe in the inward conception of the mind?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To looke vpon a woman to luſt after her: for this is adultery in heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the occaſions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 4.29. Rom. 13.13. Deut. 22.5. Mark. 6.22. Gat. 5.19. Ezec. 16.19. Gen. 19. 2 Sam. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Filthy ſongs and talke, cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering and want anneſſe, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at filthy Stage playes, putting on apparell of another ſex, mixt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcfuious dauncing, ſurferting, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, idleneſſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are wee heere com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To liue in temperance, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> and ſoberneſſe, and ſo to keepe my body holy and pure, as a Temple
<pb facs="tcp:7436:24"/>of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the eight Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is heere forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All theft and ſtealing,
<note place="margin">Deut. 22.29. Exod. 22.1.</note> which is committed many wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By violence,
<note place="margin">1 King. 21.</note> or ſecret taking away any thing which is our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Hoſ 5.10. Luk. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>By oppreſſion and tyranny of the rich towards the poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Leu. 25.14</note> 
               <hi>By deceit in buying and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By vſing any vnlawfull trade,
<note place="margin">Pro. 11.26.</note> or way of gaine, or gaming, fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling, or ſelling drinke vnto drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fifth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By prodigalitie,
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.</note> for thus doe men rob their children and poſteritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What more is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> All couetouſneſſe and vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſſe,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.25. 1 Tim. 6.10</note> the robbing of God in
<pb facs="tcp:7436:25"/>things dedicate,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30.</note> tithes and offrings.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are wee here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Math. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>To doe to all men as I would they ſhould doe vnto me, and by dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent paines taking to get mine own liuing in that eſtate of life, to which it ſhall pleaſe God to call me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the ninth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All falſe witneſſe bearing, to the abuſe and hurt of our neighbour, and all maintaining of ſuch as goe about with tales againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many wayes is this ſin committed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Foure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Deut. 19.16. 1 Kings 22.</note> 
               <hi>By falſly accuſing, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſing againſt our neighbour before a Iudge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Leu. 19.16.</note> 
               <hi>By flaundering and backbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:25"/>A.
<note place="margin">Prou. 27.14. c. 26.22.</note> 
               <hi>By flattering or ſoothing any for aduantage againſt the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>By lying,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.2. Iohn 8.45.</note> or telling an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth againſt our conſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are we here comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>As much as in vs lieth, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the good name of our neighbor,
<note place="margin">Prou. 10.22 Gal. 6.2. Pſal. 15.3. Ioſh. 7.19.</note> and our owne good name, ſtopping our eares againſt falſe reports, and ſuppreſſing them, and alwayes what ſoeuer comes of it, ſpeaking the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the tenth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife, nor his ſeruant, nor his maid, nor his oxe, nor his aſſe, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is here forbidden?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Rom 7.7. 2 Cor. 12.7 Mark. 7.22.</note> 
               <hi>All firſt motions of the mind vnto ſin, though no conſent be yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are wée commaunded heere?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To kéepe our very hearts and
<pb facs="tcp:7436:26"/>minds frée from euill thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of the Commandements of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Th. 5.23. Epheſ. 4.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the breach of the Law, and the puniſhment of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.4. Rom 7.7. Rom. 5.18. Iam. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>It is ſinne, which if it be but once committed onely, and that but in thought, it makes a man ſubiect to Gods eternall curſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is it not iuiuſtice to appoint ſo great a puniſhment for euerie ſinne? yea euen for the leaſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>It is very iuſt and right for the Lord to adiudge the leaſt ſinne to hell fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe his marke which is perfect holineſſe ſet vpon man in his creation,
<note place="margin">Iohn 8.34. Rom 6.16. 1 Iohn 3.8.</note> is hereby remooued, and a marke with the deuils brand, is made vpon the ſoule of the ſinner, for which it is iuſt, that the deuill, and not GOD, ſhould now haue ſuch a wicked ſoule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is any man able to liue without breaking theſe Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>No, not the beſt that euer
<pb facs="tcp:7436:26"/>was, except</hi> Chriſt <hi>onely, and</hi> Adam <hi>in the ſtate of innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If no man can perfectly kéepe the Law, wherefore then ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, to humble vs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.9.24 Ro. 7.12.22. Mat. 19.17. Rom. 13.8.</note> in regard of our miſerable eſtate hereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered: Secondly, to bée a rule of good life vnto vs. Thirdly, to ſet vs a worke dayly, to pray and cry to the Lord for mercy, and for ſtrength, to liue according to his Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>It is a lifting vp of the heart to God, onely in the name of Ieſus Chriſt according to his will, in full aſſurance to be heard and accepted at his gracious hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What néed is there that the faithfull pray, ſéeing God of his owne goodneſſe, and not for their prayers will doe whatſoeuer is néedfull for them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>There is great néed, that all faithfull people ſhould pray vnto God for thrée ſpeciall reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Becauſe it is a duty that wée
<pb facs="tcp:7436:27"/>owe vnto God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To renew our aſſurance of the pardon of ſinne daily renewed through our great weakeneſſe, and to increaſe our loue, patience and humility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That we may be fit to receiue the gifts and bleſſings of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What times are ſpecially to be ſpent in prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The ſpeciall times of prayer are ſixe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The preſent time without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring till ſickneſſe, or old age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The time of publike meeting to the worſhip of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Exod. 29.39</note> 
               <hi>Euery morning and euening.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fourth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.5. 1. Sam. 9.13</note> 
               <hi>Sitting downe and riſing vp from our meat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the fift?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.14. Iam. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>The time of trouble and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, when we ought more often
<pb facs="tcp:7436:27"/>and inſtantly to pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſixt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>All the dayes of our Life, through which we muſt hold out in diligent prayer, according to that of the Apoſtle, Pray continually.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.17</note>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>If we obſerue theſe times of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhall we be ſaued from all our ſinnes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes vndoubtedly,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.21.</note> for whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer calleth vpon the name of the Lord, ſhall be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is there nothing elſe required then vnto ſaluation, but to pray?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes, for wee muſt be indued with theſe properties which the Lord requireth in thoſe that pray, or elſe we ſhall pray in vaine</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many are thoſe properties?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Obedience: for not euery one that ſaith, Lord, Lord,
<note place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note> ſhall enter into heauen, but he that doth the wil of my Father which is in heauen.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Humilitie:
<note place="margin">Iam. 4.6.</note> for God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:28"/>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5 16.</note> Feruency, for the prayer of the righteous preuay leth much if it be feruent.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What more particular directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is there to be folowed in praying?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That moſt excellent prayer, which Chriſt himſelfe framed for vs, rightly therfore called the Lords Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Rehearſe the Lords Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Our Father which art in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hallowed bee thy Name: Thy kingdome come: Thy will be done in earth as it is in heauen: Giue vs this day our daily bread: And for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs: And leade vs not into temptation: But deliuer vs from euill. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Is this the onely Prayer which we are to vſe in calling vpon God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No, but we muſt bee guided by it, as by a rule, both for manner and matter in all our prayers.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>May wee not vſe it then as a Prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes doubtleſſe, we may, and
<pb facs="tcp:7436:28"/>ought to vſe it moſt often, as the chiefe of all prayers, but with great deliberation, not placing confidence in the words, but in the ſenſe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and affected in the ſaying thereof.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>It ſeemeth then that a ſet prayer is lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not onely lawfull,
<note place="margin">Num. 10.36 Pſal. 92</note> but moſt expedient, that there ſhould be a ſet forme of praying in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and to helpe the deuotion of the ignorant in priuate.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is to be thought of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued prayer? may any man vſe that?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit of God is not tyed to wordes and phraſes, but doth at times ſuddenly miniſter matter to the ſeruants of God, ſo that they can and doe pray effectually without a ſet forme, both publikely and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In what manner ought wee to pray, according to this rule of the Lords prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt,
<note place="margin">Math. 67.</note> to pray in this manner is, briefely and pithily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſecondly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:29"/>A. <hi>Propounding Gods glory, as the marke whereat wée ayme, in all our praying,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.5.</note> and not our owne vaine glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What thirdly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, and chiefly ſéeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heauenly things,
<note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> then after earthly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What fourthly?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In all things ſubmitting our wils,
<note place="margin">Mat. 26.39.</note> and deſires to the will of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What be the parts of this prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Thrée: the Preface; Our Father which are in heauen: the Petitions; Hollowed be thy name, &amp;c. and the Concluſion; For thine is the Kingdome, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In the Preface, why call you God, Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Luk. 11.11. Heb. 4.16. Gen. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.26.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe he is ready as a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father to heare mée, calling vpon his name; wherefore I learne with boldneſſe, and confidence to come vnto him in prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But may euery man come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, as his Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No wicked man that goeth
<pb facs="tcp:7436:29"/>on impenitently in ſinne can call God Father,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44. Rom. 6.16.</note> becauſe he is the deuils childe, and not Gods.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Cannot a wicked man pray then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No,
<note place="margin">Prou. 15.8. Eſa. 1.12.</note> he cannot pray with any comfort, for the prayer of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is abomination to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why doe you ſay, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and not my Father?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Tim 2.2. Matth. 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe I ought to pray for all other the children of God, aſwell as for my ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why adde you in the preface, Which art in heauen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Not for that I beléeue God to be in heauen only, for he is euery where.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>Why then?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Kin. 8.27, Pſal. 19.1. Luke 18. Luke 1.53. Eſay 66.2.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe to bée in heauen is an Argument of great glory: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I learne with reuerence to pray vnto him, béeing my Father moſt glorious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What doſt thou aske of God in this prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I deſire my Lord God our heauenly Father, who is the giuer
<pb facs="tcp:7436:30"/>of all goodneſſe, to ſend his grace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me and to all people, that we may worſhip him, ſerue him, and obey him, as wee ought to doe. And I pray vnto God, that hee will ſend vs all things that hée néedfull both for our ſoules and bodies: and that hee will be mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs our ſinnes: And that it will pleaſe him to ſaue and defend vs from all dangers, ghoſtly and bodily: and that hée will kéepe vs from all ſinne and wickedneſſe, and from our ghoſtly enemy, and from euerlaſting death. And this I truſt hée will doe of his mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And therefore I ſay, Amen. So be it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Tell me more particularly, how many be the Petitions of this prayer?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Six, whereof the thrée former concerne Gods glory, the thrée lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter concerne our ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which he thoſe thrée concer-Gods glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Firſt, Hallowed by thy name:
<pb facs="tcp:7436:30"/>ſecondly, thy Kingdome come: third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thy will be done on earth, as it is in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In the firſt of theſe what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Prou. 16.1. 1. Cor. 10.31 Rom. 11.36</note> 
               <hi>That the name of God may be glorified in the vſe of his titles, word, and all his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>In the ſecond petition, what deſire you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.2 Pſal. 93.1. Mat. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Mat. 9.38. Eph. 6.19.</note> 
               <hi>That the number of true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuers may be daily increaſed, that Gods Kingdome of Grace being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, his Kingdome of glory may be haſtened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What pray you for in the third petition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.34. 1. Theſ. 4.3. Epheſ. 4.24. Eph. 1.16, 17</note> 
               <hi>That I and all the people of God vpon earth may as readily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey Gods will, as the Angels and Saints in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which be the thrée petitions concerning our ſelues?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The firſt; Giue vs this day, our daily bread: ſecondly, forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs; thirdly, Lead vs not into te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation,
<pb facs="tcp:7436:31"/>but deliuer vs from euill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q <hi>What pray you for in the firſt of theſe Petitions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>For all things neceſſary for this preſent life,
<note place="margin">Prou. 20.8. Gen. 28.20. Mat. 6.34.</note> and therefore wee aske but for bread, and but for this day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What pray you for in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of theſe Petitions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That God would forgiue vs all our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Mat 18.26. Luke 18.10 Pſal. 39.8. Mat 5.23.</note> as wée doe from our hearts forgiue the offences of men againſt vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What pray you for in the third of theſe Petitions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>That the Lord would not ſuffer vs to be carried away by the temptations of the world, fleſh, or deuill,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.8. Eph. 6.18. Mat. 26.21.</note> to the committing of ſin, but that he would deliuer vs from the euill of all temptation, both ſinne and damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherefore ſerueth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, For thine is the Kingdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A. <hi>It is added as a reaſon of all the Petitions, to ſtrengthen our faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:31"/>Q. <hi>What is this reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Math 6.8. Mark. 9.23. Pſal. 19.1 Epheſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>That God being both able and willing, doth certainly yéeld to thoſe our requeſts, therefore wee adde a note of confidence, and ſay, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hath the Lord made any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine promiſe to heare vs, that wee may with ſo great confidence expect a graunt of our petitions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Hee hath both promiſed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.14. Math. 7.7, 9</note> and brgeth vs to beléeue from the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of an earthly Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But God is in heauen, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, neither can we ſée or heare him ſpeaking vnto vs: what viſible and ſenſible meanes therefore hath he giuen vs, whereby we may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his promiſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Iohn 20.31. Mar. 16.16 1 Cor. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>He hath giuen vs his written word, wherein his promiſes are ſet foorth, and the holy Sacraments as ſeales for our further aſſurance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16 Gal. 1.8.</note> All the Bookes of the Old and New Teſtament, and not any other bookes or Writings what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:32"/>Q. <hi>How many, and which are theſe Bookes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Books of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are ſeuen and twentie; Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, Exodus, Leuiticus, Numbers, Deuteronomy, Ioſhua, Iudges, Ruth, the firſt &amp; ſecond of Samuel, the firſt and ſecond of Kings, the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of the Chronicles, Ezra, Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Eſter, Iob, Pſalmes, Prouerbes, Eccleſiaſtes, Canticles, Eſay, Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Ezechiel, Daniel, and the 12. ſmall Prophets. The Bookes of the new Teſtament are ſeuen and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; Matthew, Marke, Luke, Iohn, the Actes of the Apoſtles, the Epiſtle to the Romans, firſt and ſecond to the Corinthians, Galatians, Epheſians, Philippians, Coloſsians, two to the Theſſalonians, and two to Timothy, to Titus, to Philemon, to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews, the Epiſtle of Iames, and two of Peter, three of Iohn, of Iude, and the Reuelation of Iohn.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are not the Apocryphall Books part of the word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are not, neither haue bin euer ſo accounted in the Church
<pb facs="tcp:7436:32"/>of God, but are annexed, as being ful of good Inſtructions, and Hiſtories declaring Gods wonderfull proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ouer his people Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How is it proued, that theſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments are the word of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is prooued by their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, ſome of them being before all other bookes,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16. 2 Pet. 1.20. 1 Theſ. 2.13.</note> ſundry times oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſought to bee burnt vp by perſecutors, and yet wonderfully preſerued, and by myracle from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen confirmed, which ſhewes, that they came from heauen, and are not of mans inuention.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Are the Bookes of the Old and New Teſtament ſufficient to ſaluation without any other?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes doubtleſſe, and it is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to adde any other as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to bee likewiſe receiued:
<note place="margin">Reu. 22.18 Deut. 4.2.</note> for to doe thus, is to incurre the danger of Gods curſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Hauing this Word written, is it not ſufficient for our ſaluation, without any helpe by preaching?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is not ſufficient,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.18.</note> but it muſt alſo be ſet foorth by preaching, that
<pb facs="tcp:7436:33"/>the hard places may be rightly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14 2 Tim. 4.2 Actes 8.31</note> wee may be kept from er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and haue our dull hearts ſtirred vp to embrace it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many bee the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the New Teſtament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two onely, as generally ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluation: that is to ſay, Baptiſme, and the Supper of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What meaneſt thou by this word Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>I meane an outward and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſigne, of an inward and ſpritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace giuen vnto vs, ordained by Chriſt himſelfe as a meanes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we receiue the ſame, &amp; as a pledge to aſſure vs thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many parts be there in a Sacrament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Two: the outward viſible ſigne, &amp; the inward ſpirituall grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the outward viſible ſigne, or forme in Baptiſme?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Water, wherein the perſon baptized is dipped, or ſprinkled with it,</hi> In the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>Q. <hi>What is the inward and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>A death vnto ſinne, and a new birth vnto righteouſnes: for, being by nature borne in ſin, and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath, wee are hereby made the children of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is required of perſons to be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Repentance, wherby they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake ſinne: and Faith, whereby they ſtedfaſtly beleeue the promiſes of God made to them in that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why then are Infants bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, when by reaſon of their ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der age they cannot performe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Yes: they doe performe them by their ſureties, who promiſe and vow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both in their names: which when they come to age, themſelues are bound to performe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why was the Sacrament of the Lords Supper ordained?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>For the continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Sacrifice of the death of Chriſt, and the benefits which we receiue thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:34"/>Q. <hi>What is the outward part, or ſigne of the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Bread and Wine, which the Lord hath commanded to be receiued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the inward part or thing ſignified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The Body &amp; Blood of Chriſt, which are verely and indeed taken and receiued of the faithfull in the Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are the benefits, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we are partakers thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>The ſtrengthening and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our ſoules by the Body and Blood of Chriſt, as our bodies are by the Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is required of them which come to the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>To examine themſelues whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they repent them truely of their former ſinnes, ſtedfaſtly purpoſing to leade a new life, haue a liuely faith in Gods mercy through Chriſt, with a thankefull remembrance of his death, and bee in charitie with all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein ſtandeth true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:34"/>A. <hi>In three things; Firſt, in knowledge and acknowledgement of our ſinnes paſt: Secondly,
<note place="margin">Prou. 28.19 Iere. 3.25. Luke 13. Pſal. 51.17 Math. 5.4. 2 Cor. 7.11.</note> in godly ſorrow and griefe of heart for them: Thirdly, in a godly purpoſe to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all ſinne, and to leade a new life for all time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">Hebr. 11.1. Rom. 8.30. Iohn 6.47. Rom. 16.14 Acts 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>It is a certaine perſwaſion of the heart, wrought by the ſpirit of God, grounded vpon his promiſes, that all my ſinnes are forgiuen mee in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Wherein ſtandeth true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian loue?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>In affection, when it is the ſame towards our neighbour,
<note place="margin">Math. 19.19 1 Iohn 3 17. Iam. 2.15, 16</note> that it is towards our ſelues voyde of malice, hatred, and enuy, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of his good, as of our owne. And in action, when wee are ready to doe good vnto others, as vnto our ſelues, and to kéepe away hurt as from our ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ſhall he doe, that after examination findes not theſe things in himſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>He may not kéepe away from
<pb facs="tcp:7436:35"/>the Lords Supper, for this were a pronoking of God to wrath, neither can hee come vnto it,
<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> without offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in a higher degrée.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What may a man doe then in this caſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>Hee muſt humbly ſue vnto God for the pardon of his ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Mat. 5.24.</note> to ſtrike his hard heart, that hee may melt into teares for them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly cleaue to his Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and if there be any diſſention, he muſt goe and be reconciled to his brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What ought a man to doe at the Lords Supper?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A.
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23</note> 
               <hi>He ought thankefully to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the inward graces of God towards him, by ſéeing the outward ſignes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are theſe graces?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are three.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the firſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Lords giuing of his Son Ieſus Chriſt to death for vs, ſet forth by the Miniſters taking of the Bread and Wine,
<note place="margin">Ioh 3.16.</note> breaking and powring out, and offering them to vs all.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:35"/>Q. <hi>Which is the ſecond?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 5.30.</note> Our neere vnion vnto Chriſt, and how we haue all our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall food from him, ſet forth by our taking, eating, and inward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſting the Bread and Wine that become nouriſhment vnto vs, and are vnited to the ſubſtance of our bodies.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Which is the third?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The neare vnion that God hath made by Chriſt betwixt all the faithfull, ſet forth by the ſame Bread,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.5. Gal. 3.28.</note> being made of many graines of corne, and by the ſame Wine made of many grapes.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is to bee done after the receiuing?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. <hi>We muſt meditate of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of new obedience, renewed by this Sacrament, that we may more carefully performe it, and flie ſinne and vice all the dayes of our life.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:7436:36"/>
            <head>Godly Prayers.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Morning Prayer for a priuate Family.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull God, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, wee giue thee hearty thankes, for the ſweet ſleepe and comfortable reſt which thou haſt giuen vs this night paſt, and for that thou haſt commaunded by thy holy Word, that no man ſhould bee idle, but alwayes occupied in godly and vertuous exerciſes, euery man according to his calling; wee moſt humbly beſeech thee, that thine eyes may attend vpon vs, daily defend vs, cheriſh, comfort, and gouerne vs and all our counſels, ſtudies, and labours in ſuch wiſe, that we may ſpend and beſtow this day, and the reſidue of our whole life according to thy moſt bleſſed wil and pleaſure, ſetting thee alwayes before our eyes, liuing in thy feare, &amp; working that that may be found acceptable in thy ſight, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wrong and louing iuſtice. Alſo we beſeech thee moſt merciful God, to ſtrengthen and keepe vs in the
<pb facs="tcp:7436:36"/>faith of thy Catholike Church, &amp; kindle in vs the loue and light of thy holy ſpirit, that we may walke godly and vertuouſly in this life, die in the truth of thy word, and liue with thee in euerlaſting glory: grant this moſt mercifull Father, for thy deare Son Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, in whoſe name we further pray as he hath taught vs, ſaying, <hi>Our Father which art, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An Euening prayer for a priuate Family.</head>
               <p>ALmightie and euerliuing God, wee giue thee moſt humble and heartie thanks, that of thy free mercies thou haſt preſerued vs this day from all hurts and dangers: vouchſafe alſo we moſt humbly beſeech thee, to keepe vs this night and euer hereafter, to ſaue vs from all our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies both bodily and ghoſtly: giue our bodies quietneſſe and ſleepe, but let our minds and ſoules continually watch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, thinke on thee and thy holy Law, that when the cheerefull light of the day ſhall appeare, we being whole in body and ſoule, may ioyfully riſe againe, bee thankfull vnto thee, and diligently walke in our vocations, to our comforts, &amp; the
<pb facs="tcp:7436:37"/>glory of thy bleſſed name, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer before the receiuing of the holy Communion.</head>
               <p>O Moſt mercifull God, and heauenly Father, I miſerable and wretched ſinner, acknowledge and confeſſe, that I am not worthy the leaſt of all thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and moſt vnworthy to receiue thee vnder the roofe of my ſoule, by partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of thy moſt bleſſed body &amp; bloud, for horrible and infinite are the ſinnes wherewith I am defiled: therfore the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry entrals of my heart are troubled, and my bones doe ſhake, becauſe I finde my ſoule a moſt vnworthy gheſt, for ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly a ſupper. But thou camſt not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance: and I know, and doe conſtantly beleeue, that notwithſtanding my ſins, thou canſt make me cleane and worthy, and forgiue me my ſins: and through thy power and mercy, I beſeech thee, grant thy grace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee a ſinner, that I may worthily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to this heauenly Sacrament. Giue me grace, before I preſume to come to the receiuing hereof, I may examine my
<pb facs="tcp:7436:37"/>ſelfe, call my ſinnes to minde, and by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained and hearty repentance return vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee my Lord: make mee with heauie ſobs to confeſſe my ſinnes, and pardon all my offences: accept me into thy fauour, cleanſe me from my wickednes, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me all my ſinnes. Alſo graunt, that receiuing this thy Sacrament, I may put off the old man, which is corruption, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the luſts of errour, and be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the ſpirit of my mind; and put on the new man, which after God is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in righteouſnes &amp; holineſſe of truth: and though by nature I cannot liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpots of ſinne, yet ſo bleſſe me, that I may neuer willingly offend thee, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together depend vpon thy goodnes: and as a true penitent ſinner, repenting of my ſinnes, I may approach to thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Supper. Grant (mercifull Father) that I may alwayes worthily receiue this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sacrament &amp; memoriall of thy death, according to thy holy ordinance, that it may increaſe in me all goodnes. Be thou the buckler, and perpetual defence of my ſoule and body, that I may come vnto thy kingdome, where I ſhall behold thee face to face; whither Lord for thy mercies ſake bring me. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:38"/>
               <head>A Thankeſgiuing after the receiuing of the holy Communion.</head>
               <p>ALmighty God, which haſt vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed ſpiritually to giue me theſe holy myſteries of thy body and bloud; mortifie whatſoeuer is euil in me, and garniſh me with thy graces and vertues: renew my ſpirit, my ſoule and my body with thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent grace: frame me after thy owne hearts deſire, and grant that I may think, ſpeak, doe, and deſire all things that may pleaſe thee: purge my conſcience from dead works, to ſerue thee the liuing God I thank thee with all reuerence of mind for bidding mee a miſerable ſinner, vnto the participation of thy holy Supper, and the receiuing of all celeſtial riches, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou beſtoweſt on me particularly all the merits and good things which by thy death thou haſt purchaſed for mee, that I may be a partaker and fellow heyre of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall bleſſednes. Raiſe vp in me by this bleſſed Sacrament, a continuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thy bitter paſsion: make mee retaine it in my mind, as a ſufficien ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of my Redemption; let mee neuer doubt of the forgiueneſſe of my ſins; and
<pb facs="tcp:7436:38"/>as often as Sathan aſſayleth mee with his deadly temptations, giue me grace to run to this Sanctuary, as to a ſtrong armor of defence; ſo that no tribulation, anguiſh, perſecution, life nor death, ſeparate mee from Chriſt my Head, whereupon being made faſt by thy holy Sacrament recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, I (as a liuing member) depend: and let mee know that I am fed and refreſhed by thy body, and precious blood, that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed therewith, I giue not my ſelfe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to carnall pleaſures, but liue in all ſinceritie and truth, as it becometh thoſe that eat af the immaculat Paſchall Lamb. Giue me grace, that laying aſide all mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe and enuy, I may forgiue euery one as thou haſt forgiuen me: giue mee grace, that participating of the bread of eternall life, I may bee repleniſhed with the fruition of thy bleſſed ſight in thy ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall Paradiſe for euer: and at my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from death, appoynt mee a place, O mercifull Lord, at thy heauenly Table, where I may taſte the new wine in the kingdome of thy Father, abiding with thine elect Angels, &amp; bleſſed Saints for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:7436:39"/>
               <head>Grace before Meat.</head>
               <p>O Lord, bleſſe vnto our vſe thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, at this time prouided for our ſuſtenance, that being preſerued hereby, and comforted, wee may doe thee more laudible ſeruice vnto thy glory, who art the Authour of all good vnto vs, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace after Meate.</head>
               <p>COntinuall praiſe be vnto thee, O Lord, who doeſt continually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide ſo graciouſly for the feeding of our feeble bodies. Leade vs heereby to a taſte of our ſpirituall food; ſo that by the helpe of both wee may growe vp in thy ſeruice, both in body and ſoule, till at the laſt we attaine thy heauenly kingdome, and be for euer glorified both in ſoule and body, through Chriſt our Lord <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace before Meat.</head>
               <p>O GOD, who haſt iuſtly curſed the earth, and all things therein for the
<pb facs="tcp:7436:39"/>ſinne of man, pardon our ſinnes, turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy curſe, &amp; vouchſafe thy bleſsing vpon theſe thy gifts, which we are now to receiue, that we vſing them with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and thankfulneſſe, may obtaine by them refreſhing and nouriſhment, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Grace after Meat.</head>
               <p>MErcifull Father, who neuer ceaſeſt to doe good vnto vs, though we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe offending thee, and now more eſpecially haſt renewed thy bountie, in feeding vs with thy bleſsings. Let not the common fruition of thy benefites make vs commonly, or lightly to eſteeme of them; neither when we are fed, let vs wax wanton againſt thee, abuſing our ſtrength to the ſeruice of ſinne. But let thy perſeuerance in goodneſſe, worke in vs perſeuerance in all dutifull obedience to our liues end, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
